اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراً
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه, as we mentioned, would constantly meet,
with the people to get feedback on their leaders.
He wanted to know how the Wulaa(ولآه) were doing.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه would meet with the people to get feedback, on the Umara'a(أمرآء),
and he would take their concerns seriously, and he would act upon it.
And I'll give examples of some of the complaints that were raised against some of the wulaa(ولآه)
Some men from Bannu Asad(بنوأسد) from Kufa(كوفه).
They came to Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه,
and they complained about Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص).
Saad Bin Abi Waqas رضي الله عنه, is  one of the 10 given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة).
One of the first believers and they came and complained about him,
and they chose an interesting timing.
It happened while the Muslims and the Persians were preparing for war.
The Muslims were preparing and the Persians were preparing for the great battle of Nahwand(النہوند).
So, these men knew very well that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) especially before a battle would start,
he wanted to make sure of Wahdat-As-Saff(الوحدت الصف), the unity of the Muslims,
because the last thing you don't want to do, is go to battle when you have the disunity.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) as very, very keen on ensuring,
that the Muslims Jama'at(جماعة) is unified and one.
There's no dissent, there's no division, there's no Fitnah(فِتْنَه), there's no gossip.
He wanted to make sure that the Muslims are on one heart.
So, for them to choose that timing right before the Battle of Nahwand(نهوند) tells you something.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),when he heard their complaints. He said;
إِنَّا لدَّلِيْلَ عَلَى مَا عِنْدَ كُمْ مِنَّ الشَّرْ،نَحُوْضَاكُمْ فِيْ هَذَالْاَمْرِ، وَإِنِ سّتَعَدَّلَكُمْ مَنِ سّتَعَدُّوْ وَإَيْمُالله
لَا يَمْنَعَنِيْ ذَالِكَ مِنَ النَّظَرِ فِيْ مَا لَدَيْكُمْ وَإِنْ نَظَرُبِكُمْ
It is evident that you have evil intentions in your complaints
because you chose this timing when you know that we are preparing to meet the enemy
and the enemy is preparing to meet us.
Nevertheless, that won't prevent me from looking into your concerns.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) again, his Farasah(فراسه) is never wrong.
He said: I believe that you're lying and you are choosing this time to cause Fitnah(فِتْنَه)
because you know that we are in dire need of having unity now.
So, you know that I'm going to take your concerns very seriously and that's why you chose this timing.
But he said: Nevertheless, I'm not gonna drop this complaint I'm going to look into it.
So, he sent Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه),
Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه), was the Sahabi(صحابي),
who was entrusted with the responsibility of investigating in these issues.
Muhammad Bin Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه) is one of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار)
and by the way, he was the head of the special operations team that assassinated Ka'ab Ibn-e-Ashraf(كعب إبن ألأشرف),
under the commands Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he's very famous name in the books of Seerah(سيرة)
and the Hadith(حديث), that talks about this special mission is in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ).
So, Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه) was one of the well known Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه), he goes to Al-Kufa(ألكوفه).
And At-Tabri(ألطبري) says: He would take Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص), to each Masjid(مسجد)
and they would hold an assembly with the people, open public meeting
and in front of everyone publicly Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه) will say,
Do you have anything against your Ameer(أمير) Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص).
And At-Tabri(ألطبري) said;
Because in those days private investigations or investigations in secret, were something that they wouldn't do.
All of their investigations were done in public, public inquiry.
It's not like you go and give the Naseeha(نصيحه) in secretly and silently and not herd know,
when it came to the Wulaa(ولآه), doesn't matter if their feelings are going to be hurt
it's done in public.
Everybody comes in Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه) is there
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) is there.
If they have anything good, they would say,
if they have anything bad they would say it
and Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه), is going to report everything back to Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين).
At-Tabri(ألطبري) say;
وَلَمْ يَكُنْ أَلّعَمَلْ بِسِّرْمِنْ شَائْنِهِمْ يَوْمَ إِذٍ
They wouldn't do these inquiries privately or secretly, it was public.
They went to each Masjid(مسجد) one by one.
No one had anything bad to say about Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) nothing negative
and these men from Bannu Asad(بنوأسد) would stay quiet
because they wouldn't dare to speak against him publicly.
It's a lie and it would be exposed.
Until, they went to the Masjid(مسجد) of Bannu Abs(بنوعبس).
You have different clans in Al-Kufa(ألكوفه).
Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه) is saying; In the name of Allah, I asked you.
If you have anything negative to say about Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) to stand up and say it.
So, one man his name is Usama Bin Qatada(أسامه بن قتادة), he stood up and said;
أَللَّهُمَّ إِنْ نَشَدْتَّنَا فَإِنَّه’ لَا يَقْسِمُ بِسَّوِيَّا،
وَلَا يَعْدِلُوْ فِيْ الرَّيْعَه،
وَلَا يَغْضُوْفِيْ السَّرِيْعَهَ
This man Osama Bin Qatadah(أسامه بن قتادة), he stood up and said;
If you are asking us in the name of Allah to speak the truth then, this is the truth.
Saad(سعد) is a man, who abuses our wealth and he is unjust in his ruling
- and he does not join the Armies.
"He's a coward he stays behind".
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) Said:
أَللَّهُمَّ إِنْ كَانَ قَالَهَا كَذِبًا،
وَرِيَاعًا، وَسُمْعَةً،فَأَعْمِيْ بَصَرَ،
وَأَكْثِرْعِيَالَ،وَعَرِّضْه’‘ لِمُذِّلَّآتِلْفِتَنْْ
O Allah if he is lying and he is making these statements to boast and to show off.
Then O Allah blind his eyes and fill his house with dependence
and make him face, the misleading Fittan(فتن).
This man just stands up bluntly and makes such a lie against Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) in his face.
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) was so angry
and there's nothing you can respond back to this man it's fabricated lie, it's a lie.
So, he made this Dua(دُعَا) against him, because it's an outright lie, "slander".
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), this man he lost his sight and when he grew old
he had 10 daughters in his house and he had to take care of them.
And he would chase women in the streets, when he was an old man.
An old man with his eyebrows, covering his eyes and he is blind.
He would go around the streets chasing women.
And when they would come and prevent him from doing that and tell him;
You should have Taqwa(تقوى) in Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and stop what you're doing,
look at you, you're an old man. What are you doing?
He would say: I was hit, I was struck by the Dua(دُعَا) of a blessed man,
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص).
With other men from Bannu Asad(بنوسعد).
Saad Bin Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) made a Dua(دُعَا) against them. And Said;
اَللَّهُمَّ أَرِّضْهُمْ لِجَهْدِالّبَلَى
"O Allah make their lives difficult."
These men were all killed in a violent death.
One of them was tore into pieces by swords.
The other one was stabbed with the butts of the swords,
with the handles of the swords, until he died and on and on.... with the rest.
All of them were received the wrath of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
because of the Dua(دُعَا) of Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص).
To add to their slander
they said that Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص), doesn't know, how to pray
and he is preoccupied with hunting.
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص), he said;
إِنِّيْ لَاَوَّلْ رَجُلْ أَحْرَقَ دَمًّا مِنْ الَّمُشْرِكِيْنَ
I'm the first man in Islam to spell the blood of a Mushrik(مشرك), the disbeliever
and I'm the only one whom Rasool Allah ﷺ, sacrificed his father and mother for both.
In Ghazwa of Uhud(غزوةأحَد), Rasool Allah ﷺ would say;
إِرْمِيْ سَعْد فِدَاكَ أَبِيْ وَأُمِّيْ
O Saad(سعد) shoot them, may my mother and father be sacrifice for you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was telling Sa'ad(سعد) may my father and mother be sacrificed for you.
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص) said;
Never did Rasool Allah ﷺ combined both his father and mother for anyone but me
and then he said: And there was a time, when I was one fifth of Islam.
He was the fifth man to become Muslim.
And then Bannu Asad(بنوأسد) claim that I cannot pray.
One of the earliest Muslims given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة) and I cannot pray.
Something to learn from this, is beware of the Dua(دُعَا) of the oppressed.
Nothing stands between it and Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Allah responds to the prayers of the oppressed even if he is a nonbeliever.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Nothing stands between the Dua(دُعَا) of the oppressed and Allah.
It climbs through the heavens like a spark of lightning.
Nothing stands between it and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Also you want to be especially careful,
that none of the Aoulea(أوليآء) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, the righteous make a Dua(دُعَا) against you,
nor should we slander the Aoulea(أوليآء) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
be careful, beware of speaking against the Friends of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Sometimes that is done to appease the Kuffar(كفار) or it is done because of jealousy
or it's done because we don't agree with their method of work but be very careful.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ loves some of His servants
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ does not allow anyone to put them down.
So, be careful in the way you use your tongue.
Rasool Allah ﷺ  said: People are thrown in Hellfire on their faces
because of what their tongues reap.
It might be one of the smallest muscles in the body but it's the most dangerous.
Abu Bakr Siddiqueرضي الله عنه would hold his tongue and pull it out and say;
This is, what is getting me in trouble.
They used to say that no one deserves, a long imprisonment term, than your tongue.
Arrest it, and put it in jail and leave it there, give it a life sentence.
Because a word when it comes out of your mouth, it can never be retrieved again.
That's it! It goes out it cannot go back again.
If it said it's a done deal.
So, we need to make sure that we use our tongue wisely.
These men lost their lives because of slandering Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن ابي وقاص).
Osama Bin Qatada(أسامه بن قتادة), it took him a few seconds
to make that statement in the Masjid(مسجد), he lost his entire life
towards the end of his life an old man running down the street, he is saying;
أَصَابَتْنِيْ دَعْوَةٌ الرَّجُلٌ المُبَارَكْ
I was struck by the Dua(دُعَا) of a blessed man.
So, if you ever slandered a righteous man or woman.
If you ever spoke against any of the Aoulea(أوليآء) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
make sure that you make Istaghfar(إستغفار).
And make sure that you compensate for talking against them,
by talking for them, by praising them.
The way you do that if you spoke against the person in a meeting of 20 people,
try to find a similar meeting of 20 people and speak good about such a person.
Try to make up for the sin by a similar good deed.
إِنَّ الْحَسَانَاتْ يُذْهِبْنَى السَّيِّئَاتْ
Hasanaat(حسانات) wipe out the sayyiaat(سَيِّئَات),
the good deeds would wipe out the evil ones.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه received a complaint from one of the soldiers in Egypt.
He told Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه that
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) accused him of being a Munafiq(منافق).
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه summoneds Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) comes in.
It is established in the court of justice of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
That Amr(عمرو) in fact, did accuse this Muslim soldier of being Munafiq(منافق).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) gave the soldier a stick
and he told him to discipline Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) for what he has said, against you.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) is sitting down.
So, the soldier, now this is one of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)'s soldiers.
Very low rank and he's now holding the stick ready to hit his leader.
So, he asks, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) he said: Can anyone protect you from me now?
He said: No, go ahead and do what you're commanded to do.
The man said: I forgive you, for the sake of Allah, I forgive you for the sake of Allah.
And he let him go.
So, the honor of people in Islam is protected.
Islam protects five things.
Your Deen(دين),
Your life,
Your mind and intellect,
Your wealth
and Your Irz(عِرْضَ) your honor.
These are the five things that Shariah(شريعة) protects.
And there's a special Hadd(حدّ), called Hadd-el- Qadh( حد القض ).
The Hadd(حدّ) of slandering
and this is specific for punishing anyone who accuses a righteous Muslim women, of committing Zina(زنا).
However, it would also apply to a man who was accused with the same sin
and also, you would find similar punishment although, it might not exactly be the Qadh(قض) .
It would be a lesser form of punishment.
If a person is dishonored or if somebody was slandered,
also in such situation a person would be punished.
So, Islam takes the honor of a person very seriously and it's protected
and this soldier, he received justice from Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه
even though it was relating to his own leader, Amr bin Aas رضي الله عنه.
Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري)
and we find that all of these Wulaa(ولآه) are great Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But people can make mistakes
and it also shows that no one was above the law.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would treat everyone equally,
he could have found justification to say that the Sahabah(صحابه) are above the law
and they should be treated different than everybody else.
Because you people, you became Muslim through them and you owe it to them.
Therefore, they should not be treated equally as you, you owe it to them.
It is a favor that they have done to you.
They have sacrificed their lives and their wealth for your sake, to bring religion to you.
But that's not what Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did.
A new Muslim who just became Muslim can come in
and seek justice against a Sahabi(صحابي) who was a Muslim from day one.
Not only that a non Muslim can come in and go to court like we talked about the case
when a JEW was sitting in court with Ali Ibn Talib رضي الله عنه
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he ruled for the JEW against Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
Abdullah Ibn Umar  رضي الله عنه, he said;
We were accompanying my father, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) we were riding our camels.
When my father spotted someone who was running towards us.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه said: This is someone who wants to talk to us.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) stopped.
And this man came and as soon as he saw Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, he started crying,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him, what's the matter?
The Man said;
I drank alcohol and your Waali(وآلي), Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) flogged me.
But then he humiliated me, by driving me around town exposing me to everyone.
And he told everyone not to eat with me, not to sit with me, not to talk to me.
So, everyone boycotted me, and I was so depressed,
I was thinking about assassinating Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري)
or coming to you and asking you to relocate me to another town
where I wouldn't be known.
Or I was thinking about going away from the land of a Islam to land of Kuffr(كفر).
When Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه heard that he started crying.
He said, I would rather sacrifice this, and this, then have you go to the land of disbelief.
And then he wrote a letter to Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) and he said;
If you have drove him around the people to expose him and humiliate him,
and you have punished him in public, than I want you to sit down in public and be punished.
and if you did that in private, than I would want you to be punished in private.
And then he told Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري)
and if you want to know how serious I am about that,
try doing what you've done again, and you would see what my response would be.
He then gave this man some clothes and 200 Dirham and he told him to go back.
So, brothers and sisters, Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه, he was strict in his rule.
But he had so much mercy in his heart towards the sinners.
This man he drank alcohol.
He should have been flogged and that was it.
Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) carried the punishment further and drove him around exposing him
and humiliating him in front of everyone, asking the people to boycott him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not want the punishment to go beyond the punishment of Sharia(شريعة)
and Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه told the man
if you drank alcohol, people in the time of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة) used to drink it.
You're not the only person to drink alcohol people in Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة) used to drink it,
you've been punished, that's the end of the story.
The punishment should not carry further than that.
So, when a person commits a sin the punishment is Sharia(شريعة) should be implemented and that's it.
When a man in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ committed adultery,
he was stoned to death.
After they stoned him and he was dead.
Some of the Sahabah(صحابه) said;
This man could not stay quiet and conceal his sin
and he went and talked about it, until he was stoned like a dog.
Rasool Allah ﷺ heard that comment and stayed quiet.
But then he came across a dead animal, decomposed body, foul smell, stench
and he ﷺ told these men to go and eat from it.
They said: O Rasool Ullah can this be eaten.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
What you have said about your brother earlier is worse than eating from this dead body.
In the name of Allah, the man that you talked about has made a Toba(توبة),
if it was distributed on the people of Madina, it would be sufficient for them.
And he's now swimming in the rivers of paradise.
He has made a Toba(توبة) he was punished
and now he is in Jannah(جنة) and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ forgave him
just because he committed adultery,
it does not give you a free allowance to say whatever you want against that person,
he was punished in Shariah(شرية), that was it.!
Another man, he was a man with very loud voice.
So, his voice was helpful in war.
Because of his loud voice, he could rally the army.
And he was also very good in fighting.
He came to Abu Musa(أبوموسى) to claim his portion of the Ghanimah(غنيمه), the spoils of war, the booty.
Abu Musa(أبوموسى) gave him part of it.
He didn't give him the whole thing.
The man said: I don't want it, either give me all of it or nothing.
Abu Musa(أبوموسى) was angry by the way the man handled this.
So, he flogged him.
So, this man went to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and also Abu Musa(أبوموسى) shaved his head.
So, the man gathered collected all of his hair.
By the way, shaving the head was a punishment in those days, it was a sign of humiliation.
Shaving the head was a sign of humiliation, it's not stylish.
People only used to shave their heads in Hajj(حَجْ) or Umrah(عمرة) or if they were punished.
It was not Sunnah(سنة) to shave their head in those days.
So, this man his head was shaved as a punishment,
he collected this hair and he went to Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين)
and he came in to see Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and he threw the hair on the chest of Umar رضي الله عنه and he said;
If it wasn't for Allah and Hellfire.
Meaning if, it wasn't for Allah and my fear of Hellfire, I would have done so and so.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him, what happened?
So, the man said: I came to claim my share of the booty.
Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) refused to give it to me
and then when I argued with him, he lashed me.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه had Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري), come to him,
and he gave the whip to this man and told him, take revenge for what he has done against you.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), these were not men of hatred and evil hearts
they just wanted justice.
So, when he received justice when it was it his hands.
He told Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) go! I have forgiven you for the sake of Allah.
Same thing that happened with Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) happens here again.
But they wanted to make a point.
They wanted to prove that we are going to get justice
and we are going to forgive when we have the capability of forgiving.
So, it makes a difference when you forgive and you're able to forgive.
And when you think that you're forgiving when really you only forgiving
because there's nothing else you could do.
There's a difference between both situations.
You get the Ajar(أجر) of forgiving when you are in a position of strength
and you are able to take revenge and then you forgive
that is the forgiveness in which you are rewarded
but when you're the underdog, the weaker one
and then you say, no I forgave him for the sake of Allah
and trying to claim credit for it, to justify your weakness that's something else.
So, over here he had a whip in his hand and
he could have disciplined Abu Musa Al Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري),
but he told him: I forgive you for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Go you are free!
Saeed Ibn Aamir(سعيدإبن عامر), one of the Zuhaad(زهاد) of the Sahabah(صحابه),
he was appointed over HIMS(حمص) in Syria.
When Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه met with the delegation of Syria, or the people of Syria from HIMS
he asked them about Saeed Ibn Aamir(سعيدإبن عامر),
How is he?
They said: We have no complaints against him except for four things.
Number 1)
He shows up to work late.
Number 2)
We would never see him at night,
we might have an emergency need, we would knock on his door
they didn't really have doors in those days, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) we'll talk about that.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) banned his governors from having doors.
So, they will come and call them actually, from their name.
He would never come out at night.
Number 3)
One day per week, he would disappear, we have no idea where he goes.
Number 4)
Sometimes he would be sitting in court and he would just fall unconscious,
he would just drop.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was worried
because his Farasah(فراسہ), his intuition about Saeed Ibn Aamir(سعيدإبن عامر), was that he was one of the best.
So, he was very concerned when he heard these accusations.
In fact, he said when he heard the first one, he shows up late to work,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
"إِنَّهَاالّعَظِيْمَهْ"
This is a great fatal mistake.
How come he's going to work late.?
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him; to come and to face his accusers in court.
So, he asked them first what complaints do you have?
They said: Number one, he shows up late to work.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said:
يا سعيد أجب
Answer, respond!
Saeed(سعيد) said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), Please forgive me!.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You must answer.
He said: I don't like to but I will.
The reason why I come out late is because I don't have a servant to take care of my needs.
So, I have to cook my own breakfast and when it's done.
"He has to prepare the dough and then bake it and cook it and that's why I come out late".
I have to cook my meal by myself.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: What is the second count.
They said: Number two,
he would never come out at night.
Answer Saeed(سعيد);
Saeed(سعيد) Said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), I have devoted my day for them
and I have devoted night for Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
They get half of my 24 hours and the other half goes to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
I have to pray, I have to recite Qur'an, I have to make Zikr(زكر).
The third count.
He doesn't show up one day per week, he disappears.
He said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) because I don't have a servant
and I only have one set of clothes, I go out to wash my clothes
and then I have to wait until they are dry and then I go back.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: What about the forth count.
They said: He would sometimes fall unconscious, in court.
He said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), when I was young and a Mushrik(مشرك) in Makkah.
I witnessed the execution of Khubaib Al Ansari(خبيب ألأنصاري).
Khubaib Al Ansari(خبيب ألأنصاري) was one of the companions  of Rasool Allah ﷺ from Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار).
He was captured by the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and they took him to Makkah and they executed him.
Saeed Ibn Aamir(سعيدإبن عامر) witnessed the execution.
Saeed(سعيد) Said: They were cutting off the flesh from the body of Khubaib(خبيب).
They were cutting it off, to make him suffer and die a slow death.
And then they crucified him and they asked him?.
They said: Khubaib(خبيب) would you rather have Rasool Allah ﷺ in your place?
Khubaib(خبيب) said: I would not want to be with my family with my kids
in the comfort and security of my house.
And have Rasool Allah ﷺ hit with a thorn.
Saeed(سعيد) said: When I remembered that day, when he was executed,
and I did nothing to help him.
When I remembered that I feel that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will never forgive me.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) that was done when he was a Mushrik(مشرك)
that happened when he was not held accountable for what he was doing
that was before Islam.
Nevertheless, he was so hurt and affected by what he saw,
and the fact that he did nothing to help Khubaib(خبيب)
not because it's his brother, and he wasn't a Muslim yet.
But as a human being, who has a dignity and believes in rights for others.
I should have done something on that day to help Khubaib Al-Ansari(خبيب ألأنصاري).
I kind of wonder how, they have such high sensitivity.
And then when you compare it to the Muslims today,
when we see in front of our eyes and in our own locality,
we're not talking about Muslims and faraway lands.
Muslims in our own locality could be abused, could be arrested, could be slandered
and we do nothing about it, we don't speak about it, we don't act to prevent it.
We just sit down, duck down as if that will protect us.
Brothers or sisters Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ holds us accountable as an Ummah(امة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: The example of this Ummah(امة) is like a body,
if one part of the body is injured, the whole body would feel the suffering and pain.
تَدَاعَلَه’ سَائِرِلّجَسَدِ بِسَّائِرِوَلْهُمَّةْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: The entire body would feel fever and loss of sleep.
Do you lose any sleep over your brothers?
Do you feel any pain when they are harmed?
If the answer is no, then you need to question your Eeman(ايمان).
If you don't feel anything, then you need to ask yourself a question.
Are you really a member of the Ummah(امة) of Muhammad ﷺ?
If you are only concerned with your own personal safety
and the safety of your direct relatives your family,
that is not the Islam that the Sahaba رضي الله عنهم believed in.
Saeed Ibn Aamir(سعيدإبن عامر) used to get these flashbacks and he would fall down unconscious
because he witnessed the execution of Khubaib(خبيب) but he did nothing
and now our brothers are falling down, one after another
and some Muslims are in fact not only are they doing nothing.
When that happens they're so terrified and afraid.
They do less then, they what they were doing before
as if that's going to protect them and save them.
That won't because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
If you forsake a Muslim brother when he is in need of help
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will forsake you when you are in need of help.
It's going to come back to you and you have to pay for it.
If you forsake a Muslim brother when he is in need of help and you have ability to help him.
Then when you face trouble, it's going to get to you.
So, if you want to protect yourself,
you need to do something to protect the Muslim brother that goes down before you.
That's the only way in which you could protect your own self
we're not now talking about helping them.
Your help your own self.
Do it for the sake of yourself and your family.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه would discipline, his Wulaa(ولآه), he would punish them.
He sent one of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) to be a governor, in Al-Heira(ألحيرة).
So, he arrives in Al-Heira(ألحيرة)
and he was invited to the house of the chief of Al-Heira(ألحيرة),
the tribal leader of Al-Heira(ألحيرة), very noble, well known man in his town.
The Ansari(أنصاري) starts joking and after he finished his food, you know, playing around.
He called the host and he wipes his hands on beard of his host.
He was joking, playing around, He wasn't serious.
This man went to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and he said;
I have served Kisra(كسرى) and Qaiser(قيصر), the Roman emperor and the Persian Emperor,
but I have never been humiliated, like, I've been humiliated by your governor.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: What did he do?
He said: He came to my house, and after I feed him, I served him
he wipes his hands on my beard.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) calls the Ansari(أنصاري) and said;
If it wasn't going to be Sunnah(سنة) after me.
I would have plucked out every hair in your own beard.
But go away, you will never ever assume any responsibility in my life.
He fired him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would not tolerate making fun of others, even if it's a joke.
And that's a problem with joking, sometimes it gets overboard.
You know, you become very light headed when you laugh a lot,
and you do things that you're not supposed to do,
and you could insult your Muslim brother.
So, Islam doesn't say that you're not allowed to have fun.
Everything should be done in moderation,
Israaf(اِسراف) is something that is not accepted in Islam,
doing anything in excess is not proper.
And, some people, they have this nature of their fun loving, and they joke a lot.
And sometimes these people would be dealing with people who tend to be serious,
and they take things seriously, and they could insult them.
When all what they meant was a joke.
Be careful, don't do that, because not everybody takes it the way you do.
And this man didn't take it as a joke, he took it as an insult and a very great insult.
He said: I've never been humiliated in my life like this.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would not allow his governors to get involved in things that are none of their business.
He once appointed someone to lead an army.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) why he did that.
But this man, he gathered the soldiers, and he said;
Tell me about every sin that you have committed.
So, every one of them was going down the list, the sins that they have committed.
Maybe that soldier wanted them to make Toba(توبة).
The leader wanted them to make Toba(توبة) or something.
Anyway, when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) heard that. He said;
Woe to him, why is he doing that,
this is none of his business to ask about the sins of others.
He is exposing sins which Allah has made private
and he fired him and said: I will never appoint him to lead any army after this.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) heard that Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص)
has fitted his house with a door.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he sends Muhammad Ibn Maslimma(محمدإبن مسلمه) specifically, to go to Al-Kufa(ألكوفه).
He told him you gather some wood and you go and burn the door of Saad(سعد).
They go, they evacuated the house and they burned the door.
The reason why Saad(سعد) had that door is because his house was close to the market
and the market was very loud.
So, as an insulator he had that door that was it.
It wasn't to prevent the people from coming in.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) didn't want his governors, to have gate in compounds.
They need to be accessible.
The people need to feel that you're very close by, all what they have to do is, go next to your house
and call you and you would definitely hear them and come out.
Imagine the house of the governor is without a door.
Just open, you just walk in, after you seek permission, given.
Mojasha Bin Masood(مجاشه بن مسعود) was appointed as a governor.
So, he relocated obviously, and his wife accompanied him.
So, when they reached to their new house.
The wife wanted to renovate the house.
You Know, usually sisters, they would move into a new house and they wanted to be according to their taste.
So, in those days, mud houses didn't have any paint.
What they would do is they would cover it with cloth because it's mud.
And you would be kneeling on the wall and you would have all of this dirt
on your back, dust because it's a mad house.
So, what they would do is, they would cover it with cloth.
So, the wife of Mojasha(مجاشه) is now, remodeling the house
and she's putting all of these pieces of cloth in there.
And it was very simple it's not like today you know, I want to have hardwood floor,
but the kitchen, the title is to be white and you know everything is down to the exact details,
I mean I don't even know how to express it because I don't know the lingo for it.
There Masha Allah(ماشاء الله) Ya'ani(يعني), There could have very specific details
and they would mention colors that I never heard in my life,
but it wasn't that sophisticated all what the wife of Mojasha(مجاشه) wanted
is to have the wall covered with a piece of cloth.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) heard about that he sends a letter.
Mojasha(مجاشه) receives the letter when he was meeting with some men,
and his face changed and they sensed that.
They said: What happened?
He said: Come with me.
So, all of these men come with Mojasha(مجاشه) and they go to his house.
His wife comes out.
He said: Move out of my way.
You have put me in trouble and he gets her out of the house,
and it tells the Men to tear down, every single piece of cloth, just tear it down.
And that's why many of the women in that era
never wanted their husbands to be involved with the work with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
The wife of my Muaadh Ibn Jabal(معاذبن جبل), the wife of Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة), the wife of Mojasha(مجاشه)
because of the restrictions that he would placed on them.
You could live an easier life, if you're not employed with the government of Umar bin Khattab رضي الله عنه,
you would be better off going and doing business.
Also Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sometimes would just drop in suddenly and visit his Wulaa(ولآه).
So, he would have somebody asked for permission and he would say;
Do you permit me and the men with me, to come in
because Umar(عُمَر) did not want his name to be mentioned.
He knows that they would do some last minute changes to the furniture.
So, they would seek permission,
"لِيْ وَلِمَنْ مَعِيْ"
Me and the ones accompanying me
and then suddenly they would find Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) inside their house.
So, he landed inside the house of Yazeed Ibn Abi Sufiaan(يزيدإبن أبي سفيان).
And he saw the walls covered with cloth,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) with his own hands, he is tearing those pieces of cloth in front of Yazeed(يزيد)
and telling him;
This cloth which you are covering your walls with,
could cover the naked bodies of many Muslims
and save them from hot weather and cold weather.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would go as far as disciplining them physically with his famous stick Ad-Durra(ألدّره),
he did that a couple of times
not only did he use a durra(درَّة) but once when he went to Ash-Sham(ألشام),
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة), Yazeed Ibn Abi Sufiaan(يزيدإبن أبي سفيان) and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
they came to meet, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه and they had some nice clothes on.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) saw them he came down from this camel.
Picked up some rocks and started throwing at them,
pelting Yazeed(يزيد), Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) and Khalid(خالد) imagine throwing rocks at them.
And then he said;
مَا أَسْرَأَ مَا رَجَعْتُمْ أَنْ رَّيْكُمْ،إِيَّايَ تَسْتَقْبِلُوْنَ فِيْ هَذَا ذِّي
How fast have you changed your ways?
How dare you meet me with these clothes?
وَإِنَّمَا شَبِئْتُمْ مُنْزُ سَنَتَيْنَ
You only knew wealth two years ago.
وَبِاللهِ وَلَوْ فَعَلْتُمْ هَذَا عَلَى رَئْسِلْ مِئَتَيْنِ لَسْتَبْدِلْ بِكُمْ غَيْرَكُمْ
In the name of Allah. If you did this after 200 years from now, I wouldn't have accepted it.
He is telling them two years ago, you are poor.
And now you tasted wealth and you already changed within two years.
Even if you are wealthy for 200 years, I wouldn't have allowed this change to show on you.
You're working with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), you're gonna have to carry on with the old ways,
even if it's going to last for 200 years.
He reduced the status of one of his governors from being a governor, to being a shepherd
Ayaaz Bin Ghanam(أياز بن غنم), he appointed him as a governor.
So, Ayaaz(أياز) he built a new house and he built himself a bath
and he also had a special group
which he would spend his night with and talk with exclusive group.
And this was not accessible for the rest of the people,
special group that are close to the Ameer(أمير).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) call him to Madina, he comes in, he brings 300 sheep.
He gives it to him and he gives him a wool rough Thaub(ثوب), he tells him wear this.
And then he tells him: Take these goats or sheep.
So, he would walk away
and when he is far from Umar(عُمَر), Umar(عُمَر) would tell him: Come back, come back.
And he's next to Umar(عُمَر), go away. You go away, come back.
And you would have him go back and forth with the 300 sheep until, he started sweating.
And then he said: Go and take them out to the pasture land and then come back.
He would go out to the pasture land and come back, go and water them
and he would have him go back and forth for two months.
After two months, he told him: Do you still want a bath in your house?
Do you still want to have an exclusive group around you?
He said: No Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), that's it, I don't want that anymore.
Toba(توبة)! I repent to Allah.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), this disciplining made Ayaaz Bin Ghanam(أياز بن غنم)
one of the best governors of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
He would ask them to split their wealth in half, after they leave their job.
We said earlier that he would take the difference.
Over here it's contradicting narration.
It says that for example, they started,
so he would hold an account for them before they assume the job.
Let's say they had 1000 Dinar(دينار).
After he removes them from the job.
Let's say they had 2000 Dinar(دينار).
So, the difference is a 1000 Dinar(دينار).
They made a 1000 Dinar(دينار) within that period.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would ask them to split it in half.
Allah Ho Alam(ألله أعلم) which narration is stronger.
But I'm mentioning to you both.
That's what he did with Khalid Ibn Waleed رضي الله عنه.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: He split everything in half, even my shoes.
He would take one pair, he would take one and we give me one.
He would reprimand them verbally and he would write letters to them.
When he went to meet with Muawiya Bin Abi Sufiyan(معاويه بن أبي سفيان).
Muawiya(معاويه) came to meet him in an entourage.
Muawiya(معاويه) is the new governor in Syria and he comes to meet
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه and he is surrounded by guards.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was riding his camel.
Muawiya(معاويه) came down out of respect to greet the Khalifah(خليفه).
The Khalifah(خليفه) ignores him and he is walking away on his camel
and Muawiya(معاويه) is now running on foot after the Khalifah(خليفه),
trying to get his attention, and Muawiya(معاويه) was a heavy man.
So, he was catching his breath, he was gasping
and Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه is ignoring him.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) felt pity for Muawiya(معاويه).
He said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين),
"أَتَعَبْتَ الرَّجُلْ"
He is exhausted.
Please talk to him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) turns around and said;
Who does this entourage belong to?
He said: It belongs to me.
He said: It belongs to you and in addition to that, I hear that you have an officer
who stands between you and men.
When people want to meet you?
You had a secretary, now Muawiya(معاويه) had a secretary,
if you want to meet Muawiya(معاويه) you have to come through his secretary.
Muawiya(معاويه) said: Yes.
He said: Woe to you. Why did you do that?
Muawiya(معاويه) said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) in this land of ours,
there are plenty of spies planted by our enemy.
If they see us moving around without heavy security.
They might take advantage of that and attack us
and the reason, why I have a secretary
is because I don't want the people to take advantage of us.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه said: O Muawiya(معاويه),
whenever, I ask you about something you have a justification for it.
If what you're saying is true.
That is very intelligent of you
and if what you're saying is a lie, that's a very clever lie.
I do not approve or disapprove what you're doing.
He left it at that.
because Muawiya(معاويه) told him after he mentioned his justification is he said;
And after that I am only your servant.
If you tell me to go on with it, I would,
- if you tell me to stop, I would.
So, Umar(عُمَر) said: You know how to get out of trouble.
Tayeb(طيب)
In Sha Allah Ho Ta'ala(إن شاء الله تعالى) tomorrow night,
we will either move on to the section on the Ghazawaat(غزوات) , the battles,
or we will jump ahead and talk about the death of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and then talk about the battles, after that.
So, we're done with the section relating to the Wulaa(وُلأء) of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE